Inventory of the Joel E. Spingarn Papers 1934-1938
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Joel E. Spingarn Papers, 1934-1938.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Small Collections Spingarn
17 items.
Letters written to Joel E. Spingarn.
Joel E. Spingarn
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 17 items, 1964.
Biographical/Historical Information
Joel E. Spingarn was born May 17, 1875 in New York City. He received a doctorate from Columbia University. He was a professor at Columbia but left academic life in 1911. He was a poet, editor and critic as well as a social reformer. He was an early member of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People and he established the Spingarn Medal. He served as NAACP president in the 1930's. He died July 26, 1939.
Scope and Content Information
Includes letters to Spingarn, president of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People from Lowell Thomas, Sumner Welles, Edward Steichen, Charles A. Beard, Henry F. Du Pont, H. L. Menchen and Owen Roberts concerning horticultural matters. Also includes correspondence, 1938, of Congressman Hamilton Fish, Jr., Walter White, and Springarn concerning remarks made by William E. Borah concerning lynching.
Arrangement
The collection is mostly chronological.
Additional Descriptive Data
Related Materials
The main collections of Joel E. Spingarn papers are in the New York Public Library, Howard University, and in the James Weldon Johnson Collection at Yale University.There are also materials at the Library of Congress.
Index Terms
Subjects:
National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.; Lynching--United States--History.; Horticulture.; Afro-Americans.
Persons
Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940.; Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981.; Welles, Sumner, 1892-1961; Steichen, Edward, 1879-1973.; Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.; Du Pont, Henry Francis, 1880-1969.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880- 1956.; Roberts, Owen J. (Owen Josephus), 1875-1955.; Fish, Hamilton, 1888; White, Walter Francis, 1893- 1955.
Contents List
- Hendrik Willem van Loon in New York City and Guinea to Spingarn, January-March 1934., 2 items. (Folder 1)
- May Eastman at Croton-on-Hudson, New York to Spingarn, 19 January 1934., TLS. (Folder 2)
- Lowell Thomas, New York City, to Spingarn, 7 May 1935., TLS. (Folder 3)
- Sumner Welles in Washington, D.C., to J.E. Spingarn in Amenia, Duchess County, New York, 9 April 1936. (Folder 4)
- Edward Steichen of the Amer. Delphinium Soc. in New York City, to J.E. Spingarn, Amenia, New York, 26 May 1936. (Folder 5)
- M. A. LeHand, private Secretary to the President, the White House, Washington, D.C. to J.E. Spingarn, Pres. of the Natl. Assn. for Advancem. of Col. People in New York City, 4 Nov[ember]1937., TLS. (Folder 6)
- Charles Beard to Spingarn, 3 Nov. [?], ALS. (Folder 7)
- Phylis Moore, Willbrook House, Rathfarnham County, Dublin [Ireland] to [J.E.] Springarn 13 Feb[ruary] 1934, ALS. (Folder 8)
- Lord Aberconway, Bodanant Tal-y-Cafn, N. Wales, to J.E. S[pingarn], Troutbeck, Amenia, New York, U.S.A., 21 Oct. 1935., TLS. (Folder 9)
- Hamilton Fish, Jr., Congress of the U. S. to J.E.S[pingarn], New York City, 3 Mar. 1936., 4 items. (Folder 10)
  Attached are copies of letters from Fish to Walter White, Nat[io]n[a]l Assn. for Advancem[ent] of Col[ored] People, the reply of White and printed copy of remarks of Fish on Senator Borah and the AntiLynching Bill
- Owen Roberts to [J.E.Spingarn], 6 Apr[il] 1937. (Folder 11)
- Henry F. DuPont, Winterthur, Delaware, to J.E.S[pingarn], Troutbeck, Amenia, New York, 9 April 1937, TLS. (Folder 12)
- H. L. Mencken, Baltimore, Maryland, to [J.E.] Spingarn, 3 Nov[ember] 1937., TLS. (Folder 13)